<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!--
  ~ Copyright (c) 2008-2012, Hazel Bilisim Ltd. All Rights Reserved.
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->

<sect1 xml:id="InternalsClusterMembership" version='5.0' xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
        >
    <title>Internals 3: Cluster Membership</title>
    <para>It is important to note that Hazelcast is a peer to peer clustering so there is no
        'master' kind of server in Hazelcast. Every member in the cluster is equal and has the same
        rights and responsibilities.
    </para>
    <para>When a node starts up, it will check to see if there is already a cluster in the network.
        There are two ways to find this out:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Multicast discovery: If multicast discovery is enabled (that is the defualt)
                    then the node will send a join request in the form of a multicast datagram
                    packet.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Unicast discovery: if multicast discovery is disabled and
                    <literal>TCP/IP</literal>
                    join is enabled then the node will try to connect
                    to he IPs defined in the
                    <literal>hazelcast.xml</literal>
                    configuration file. If
                    it can successfully connect to at least one node, then it will send a join
                    request through the
                    <literal>TCP/IP</literal>
                    connection.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        If there is no existing node, then the node will be the first member of the
        cluster. If multicast is enabled then it will start a multicast listener so that it can
        respond to incoming join requests. Otherwise it will listen for join request coming
        via<literal>TCP/IP</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>If there is an existing cluster already, then the oldest member in the cluster will
        receive the join request and check if the request is for the right group. If so, the oldest
        member in the cluster will start the join process.
    </para>
    <para>In the join process, the oldest member will:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>send the new member list to all members</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>tell members to sync data in order to balance the data load</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        Every member in the cluster has the same member list in the same order.
        First member is the oldest member so if the oldest member dies, second member in the list
        becomes the first member in the list and the new oldest member.
    </para>
    <para>See
        <literal>com.hazelcast.impl.Node</literal>
        and
        <literal>com.hazelcast.impl.ClusterManager</literal>
        for details.
    </para>
    <para>
        <emphasis role="italic">
            <emphasis role="bold">Q. If, let say 50+, nodes are trying to join
                the cluster at the same time, are they going to join the cluster one by
                one?
            </emphasis>
        </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>No. As soon as the oldest member receives the first valid join request, it will wait 5
        seconds for others to join so that it can join multiple members in one shot. If there is no
        new node willing to join for the next 5 seconds, then oldest member will start the join
        process. If a member leaves the cluster though, because of a JVM crash for example, cluster
        will immediately take action and oldest member will start the data recovery process.
    </para>
</sect1>
