<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!--
  ~ Copyright (c) 2008-2012, Hazel Bilisim Ltd. All Rights Reserved.
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->

<sect1 xml:id="InternalsDistributedMap" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
       xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
       xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
       xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
       http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink.xsd">
    <title>Internals 4: Distributed Map</title>
    <para>Hazelcast distributed map is a peer to peer, partitioned implementation so entries put
        into the map will be almost evenly partitioned onto the existing members. Entries are
        partitioned according to their keys.
    </para>
    <para>Every key is owned by a member. So every key-aware operation, such as
        <literal>put,
            remove, get
        </literal>
        is routed to the member owning the key.
    </para>
    <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">
            <emphasis role="italic">
                Q. How does Hazelcast determine the owner of a key?
            </emphasis>
        </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>Hazelcast creates fixed number of virtual partitions (blocks). Partition count is set to
        <literal>271</literal>
        by default. Each key falls into one of these partitions. Each
        partition is owned/managed by a member. Oldest member of the cluster will assign the
        ownerships of the partitions and let every member know who owns which partitions. So at any
        given time, each member knows the owner member of a each partition. Hazelcast will convert
        your key object to
        <literal>com.hazelcast.nio.Data</literal>
        then calculate the partition of
        the owner:<literal>partition-of-the-key = hash(keyData) % PARTITION_COUNT</literal>. Since
        each member(JVM) knows the owner of each partition, each member can find out which member
        owns the key.
    </para>
    <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">
            <emphasis role="italic">
                Q. Can I get the owner of a key?
            </emphasis>
        </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>Yes. Use Partition API to get the partition that your key falls into and then get the
        owner of that partition. Note that owner of the partition can change over time as new
        members join or existing members leave the cluster.<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[PartitionService partitionService = Hazelcast.getPartitionService();
Partition partition = partitionService.getPartition(key);
Member ownerMember = partition.getOwner();
]]></programlisting>Locally owned entries can be obtained by
        calling<literal>map.localKeySet()</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">
            <emphasis role="italic">
                Q. What happens when a new member joins?
            </emphasis>
        </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>Just like any other member in the cluster, the oldest member also knows who owns which
        partition and what the oldest member knows is always right. The oldest member is also
        responsible for redistributing the partition ownerships when a new member joins. Since there
        is new member, oldest member will take ownership of some of the partitions and give them to
        the new member. It will try to move the least amount of data possible. New ownership
        information of all partitions is then sent to all members.
    </para>
    <para>Notice that the new ownership information may not reach each member at the same time and
        the cluster never stops responding to user map operations even during joins so if a member
        routes the operation to a wrong member, target member will tell the caller to
        <literal>re-do</literal>
        the operation.
    </para>
    <para>If a member's partition is given to the new member, then the member will send all entries
        of that partition to the new member (Migrating the entries). Eventually every member in the
        cluster will own almost same number of partitions, and almost same number of entries. Also
        eventually every member will know the owner of each partition (and each key).
    </para>
    <para>You can listen for migration events.
        <literal>MigrationEvent</literal>
        contains
        the<literal>partitionId</literal>,<literal>oldOwner</literal>, and
        <literal>newOwner</literal>
        information.
        <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[PartitionService partitionService = Hazelcast.getPartitionService();
partitionService.addMigrationListener(new MigrationListener () {

   public void migrationStarted(MigrationEvent migrationEvent) {
      System.out.println(migrationEvent);
   }

   public void migrationCompleted(MigrationEvent migrationEvent) {
      System.out.println(migrationEvent);
   }
});
]]></programlisting>
        <emphasis role="bold">
            <emphasis role="italic">Q. How about distributed set and
                list?
            </emphasis>
        </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>Both distributed set and list are implemented on top of distributed map. The underlying
        distributed map doesn't hold value; it only knows the key. Items added to both list and set
        are treated as keys. Unlike distributed set, since distributed list can have duplicate
        items, if an existing item is added again,
        <literal>copyCount</literal>
        of the entry
        (<literal>com.hazelcast.impl.ConcurrentMapManager.Record</literal>) is incremented. Also note that index
        based methods of distributed list, such as
        <literal>List.get(index)</literal>
        and<literal>List.indexOf(Object)</literal>, are not supported because it is too costly
        to keep distributed indexes of list items so it is not worth implementing.
    </para>
    <para>Check out the
        <literal>com.hazelcast.impl.ConcurrentMapManager</literal>
        class for the
        implementation. As you will see, the implementation is lock-free because
        <literal>ConcurrentMapManager</literal>
        is a singleton and processed by only one thread,
        the<literal>ServiceThread</literal>.
    </para>
</sect1>
