<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="InternalsThreads" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Internals 1: Threads</title>
    <para>In this section, we will go over the Hazelcast's internal threads, the client threads
        executing Hazelcast API and how these threads work together in Hazelcast. When developing
        Hazelcast, you should know which thread will execute your code, which variables are local to
        that thread, and how you should interact with other threads. </para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">1. Client Threads:</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>Client threads are your threads, user's application threads, and or user's application/web
        server's threads that are executing Hazelcast API. User's threads that are client to
        Hazelcast. For example, <literal>Hazelcast.getQueue("myqueue"), map.put(key, value),
            set.size()</literal> calls are initiated and finalized in the client threads.
        Serialization of the objects also happens in the client threads. This also eliminates the
        problems associated with classloaders. Client threads initiate the calls, serialize the
        objects into Hazelcast <literal>com.hazelcast.nio.Data</literal> object which holds
            a<literal>java.nio.ByteBuffer</literal>. `Data` object is the binary representation of
        the application objects (key, value, item, callable objects). All Hazelcast threads such
            as<literal>ServiceThread</literal>, <literal>InThread</literal> and
            <literal>OutThread</literal> work with <literal>Data</literal> objects; they don't know
        anything about the actual application objects. When the calls are finalized, if the return
        type is an object, `Data` object is returned to the client thread and client thread then
        will deserialize the `Data` (binary representation) back to the application objects. </para>
    <para>For each client thread, there is a <literal>com.hazelcast.impl.ThreadContext</literal>
        thread-local instance attached which contains thread context information such as
        transaction. </para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">2. <literal>ServiceThread</literal>:</emphasis></para>
    <para>`ServiceThread`, implemented at `com.hazelcast.impl.ClusterService`, is the most
        significant thread in Hazelcast. Almost all none-IO operations happens in this thread.
        `ServiceThread` serves to local client calls and the calls from other members. </para>
    <para>If you look at the <literal>ClusterService</literal> class you will see it is constantly
        dequeueing its queue and processing local and remote events.
            <literal>ClusterService</literal> queue receives local events in the form of
            <literal>com.hazelcast.impl.BaseManager.Processable</literal> instances and remote
        events in the form of <literal>com.hazelcast.nio.PacketQueue.Packet</literal> instances
            from<literal>InThread</literal>. </para>
    <para>All distributed data structures (queue, map, set) are eventually modified in this thread
        so there is -no- synchronization needed when data structures are accessed/modified. </para>
    <para>It is important to understand that client threads initiates/finalizes the calls, in/out
        threads handles the socket read/writes and <literal>ServiceThread</literal> does the
        actually manipulation of the data structures. There is no other threads allowed to touch the
        data structures (maps, queues) so that there is no need to protect the data structures from
        multithread access: no synchronization when accessing data structures. It may sound
        inefficient to allow only one thread to do all data structure updates but here is the logic
        behind it (Please note that numbers given here are not exact but should give you an idea.):
        If there is only one member (no IO), <literal>ServiceThread</literal> utilization will be
        about 95% and it will process between 30K and 120K operations per second, depending on the
        server. As the number of members in the cluster increases, IO Threads will be using more CPU
        and eventually <literal>ServiceThread</literal> will go down to 35% CPU utilization so
            <literal>ServiceThread</literal> will process between 10K and 40K operations per second.
            <literal>ServiceThread</literal> CPU utilization will be at about 35% regardless of the
        size of the cluster. (The only thing that can affect that would be the network utilization.)
        This also means that total number of operations processed by the entire cluster will be
        between N*10K and N*40K; N being the number of nodes in the cluster. About half of these
        operations will be backup operations (assuming one backup) so client threads will realize
        between N*5K and N*20K operations per second in total. Since there is only one thread
        accessing the data structures, increase in the number of nodes doesn't create any contention
        so access to the data structures will be always at the same speed. This is very important
        for Hazelcast's scalability. </para>
    <para>This also makes writing code super easy because significant portion of the code is
        actually single-threaded so it is less error-prone and easily maintainable. </para>
    <para>No synchronization or long running jobs are allowed in this thread. All operations running
        in this thread have to complete in microseconds. </para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">3. <literal>InThread</literal> and<literal>OutThread</literal>:
        </emphasis></para>
    <para>Hazelcast separates reads and writes by having two separate threads; one for reading, and
        the other for writing. Eache IO thread uses its own <literal>NIO</literal> selector
        instance. <literal>InThread</literal> handles <literal>OP_ACCEPT</literal> and
            <literal>OP_READ</literal> socket operations while <literal>OutThread</literal> handles
            <literal>OP_CONNECT</literal> and <literal>OP_WRITE</literal> operations. </para>
    <para>Each thread has its queue that they dequeue to register these operations with their
        selectors so operation registrations and operation processing happens in the same threads. </para>
    <para>`InThread`'s runnable is the `com.hazelcast.nio.InSelector` and `OutThread`'s runnable is
        the `com.hazelcast.nio.OutSelector`. They both extends `SelectorBase` which constantly
        processes its registration queue ('selectorQueue') and the selectedKeys. </para>
    <para>Members are connected to each other via<literal>TCP/IP</literal>. If there are N number of
        members in the cluster then there will be <literal>N*(N-1)</literal> connection end point
        and <literal>(N*(N-1))/2</literal> connections. There can be only one connection between two
        members, meaning, if m2 creates a connection to m1, m1 doesn't create another connection to
        m2 and the rule here is that new members connect to the older members. </para>
    <para>If you look at the <literal>com.hazelcast.nio.Connection</literal>, you will see that each
        connection is representing a socket channel and has
            <literal>com.hazelcast.nio.ReadHandler</literal> and <literal>WriteHandler</literal>
        instances which are attached to the socket channel's <literal>OP_READ</literal> and
            <literal>OP_WRITE</literal> operation selectionKeys respectively. When
            <literal>InSelector</literal> selects <literal>OP_READ</literal> selection key (when
        this operation is ready for the selector), <literal>InSelector</literal> will get the
        attached <literal>ReadHandler</literal> instance from the selectionKey and call its
            <literal>ReadHandler.handle()</literal> method. Same for
            the<literal>OutSelector</literal>. When <literal>OutSelector</literal> selects
            <literal>OP_WRITE</literal> selection key (when this operation is ready for the
        selector), <literal>OutSelector</literal> will get the attached
            <literal>WriteHandler</literal> instance from the selectionKey and call its
            <literal>WriteHandler.handle()</literal> method. </para>
    <para>When <literal>ServiceThread</literal> wants to send an Invocation instance to a member, it
        will <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>get the Connection for this member by calling
                        <literal>com.hazelcast.nio.ConnectionManager.get().getConnection(address)</literal></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>check if the connection is live; Connection.live()</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>if live, it will get the <literal>WriteHandler</literal> instance of the
                    Connection</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>enqueue the invocation into the<literal>WriteHandler</literal>'s queue</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>and add registration task into<literal>OutSelector</literal>'s queue, if
                    necessary</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><literal>OutSelector</literal> processes the <literal>OP_WRITE</literal>
                    operation registration with its selector </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>when the selector is ready for the <literal>OP_WRITE</literal> operation,
                        <literal>OutSelector</literal> will get the <literal>WriteHandler</literal>
                    instance from selectionKey and call
                    its<literal>WriteHandler.handle()</literal></para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist><emphasis role="italic">see</emphasis>
        <literal>com.hazelcast.impl.BaseManager.send(Packet, Address)</literal>. </para>
    <para><emphasis role="italic">see</emphasis>
        <literal>com.hazelcast.nio.SelectorBase.run()</literal>. </para>
    <para>Connections are always registered/interested for <literal>OP_READ</literal> operations.
        When <literal>InSelector</literal> is ready for reading from a socket channel, it will get
        the <literal>ReadHandler</literal> instance from the selectionKey and call its handle()
        method. handle() method will read Invocation instances from the underlying socket and when
        an Invocation instance is fully read, it will enqueue it
            into<literal>ServiceThread</literal>'s (`ClusterService` class) queue to be processed. </para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">4. <literal>MulticastThread</literal>: </emphasis></para>
    <para>If multicast discovery is enabled (this is the default), and node is the master (oldest
        member) in the cluster then <literal>MulticastThread</literal> is started to listen for join
        requests from the new members. When it receives join request
        (`com.hazelcast.nio.MulticastService.JoinInfo` class), it will check if the node is allowed
        to join, if so, it will send its address to the sender so that the sender node can create a
            <literal>TCP/IP</literal> connection to the master and send
            a<literal>JoinRequest</literal>. </para>
  
    <para><emphasis role="bold">5. Executor Threads:</emphasis></para>
    
    <para>Each node employs a local <literal>ExecutorService</literal> threads which handle the
        event listener calls and distributed executions. Number of core and max threads can be
        configured. </para>
</sect1>
