<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 xml:id="MC_Intro" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
       xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
       xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
        Hazelcast Management Center enables you to monitor and manage your servers running hazelcast.
        With Management Center besides observing overall state of your clusters, you can also analyse and browse your data structures in details.
        It has capabilities that you can configure your cluster on runtime, such as configuring your map properties, taking thread dump from nodes.
        With its scripting module you can run actions on your servers with javascript.
        Version 2.0 is a web based tool so you can deploy it into your internal server and serve your users.
    </para>
    <sect2 xml:id="MC_Installation" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
            >
        <title>Installation</title>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para> Download latest hazelcast from <link xlink:href="http://www.hazelcast.com/downloads.jsp">hazelcast.com</link></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Deploy the webmancenter_VERSION.war file bundled in the to your webserver (Tomcat, Jetty etc.)
                </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>   Start your web server.
                </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>   Configure your hazelcast by adding following to your hazelcast.xml
                    <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
     <management-center enabled="true" >YOUR_URL</management-center>
     ]]>
</programlisting>
                </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>      Start your hazelcast cluster
                </para>
            </listitem>


            <listitem>
                <para>  Browse your web servers url.  <emphasis role="bold">
                        Initial login credentials are: username:admin password:admin
                </emphasis>
                </para>
            </listitem>

        </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="MC_UserAdministration" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
            >
        <title>User Administration</title>
        <para>Default credentials are for admin users. Admin users can make user operations and has read/write access to all clusters. In the "Administration" tab page you can add new users, update/remove existing ones.. If you want to restrict users to only read only operations then check the "Read Only" radio button for the clusters.
            <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata contentwidth="800px"  fileref="images/admin.jpg"/>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
        </para>

    </sect2>


    <sect2 xml:id="MC_ToolOverview" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
            >
        <title>Tool Overview</title>
        <para>The starter page of the tool is "Cluster Home". Here you can see cluster's main properties such as uptime, memory. Also with pie chart you can see the distribution of partitions over cluster members. You can come back to this page, by clicking the Home icon on the right top toolbar.
            On the left panel you see the instances Maps, Queues, Topics; stored in the cluster. Below them, the members in the clusters are listed.
            On top menu bar, you can change the current page to Scripting, Docs, User Administration. Note that User Administration page is viewable only for admin users. Also Scripting page is disabled for users with read only credential for current cluster. </para>
        <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata contentwidth="800px"  fileref="images/clusterhome.jpg"/>
            </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
    </sect2>

</sect1>
