<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 xml:id="NativeClient" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
        >
    <title>Native Client</title>
    <para>Native Client enables you to do all Hazelcast operations without being a member of the
        cluster. It connects to one of the cluster members and delegates all cluster wide operations
        to it. When the relied cluster member dies, client will transparently switch to another live
        member.
    </para>
    <para>There can be hundreds, even thousands of clients connected to the cluster. But by default there is 40 threads
    on server side that will handle all the requests. You may want to increase hazelcast.executor.client.thread.count
    property for better performance. </para>
    <para>Imagine a trading application where all the trading data stored and managed in a 10 node
        Hazelcast cluster. Swing/Web applications at traders' desktops can use Native Java Client to
        access and modify the data in the Hazelcast cluster.
    </para>
    <para>Currently Hazelcast has Native Java and C# Client available.
    </para>
    <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">
            <emphasis role="italic">
                LiteMember vs. Native Client
            </emphasis>
        </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>LiteMember is a member of the cluster, it has socket connection to every member in the
        cluster and it knows where the data is so it will get to the data much faster. But LiteMember
        has the clustering overhead and it must be on the same data center even on the same
        RAC. However Native client is not member and relies on one of the cluster members. Native
        Clients can be anywhere in the LAN or WAN. It scales much better and overhead is quite less.
        So if your clients are less than Hazelcast nodes then LiteMember can be an option;
        otherwise definitely try Native Client. As a rule of thumb: Try Native client first, if it
        doesn't perform well enough for you, then consider LiteMember.
    </para>
    <para>The following picture describes the clients connecting to Hazelcast Cluster. Note the
        difference between LiteMember and Java Client
        <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="http://www.hazelcast.com/resources/hazelcast-cluster-labels.png"
                        />
            </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
    </para>
    <sect2 xml:id="JavaClient" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
            >
        <title>Java Client</title>
        <para>You can do almost all hazelcast operations with Java Client. It already implements the
            same interface. You must include hazelcast-client.jar into your classpath.
            <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[import com.hazelcast.core.HazelcastInstance;
import com.hazelcast.client.HazelcastClient;

import java.util.Map;
import java.util.Collection;


ClientConfig clientConfig = new ClientConfig();
clientConfig.getGroupConfig().setName("dev").setPassword("dev-pass");
clientConfig.addAddress("10.90.0.1", "10.90.0.2:5702");

HazelcastInstance client = HazelcastClient.newHazelcastClient(clientConfig);
//All cluster operations that you can do with ordinary HazelcastInstance
Map<String, Customer> mapCustomers = client.getMap("customers");
mapCustomers.put("1", new Customer("Joe", "Smith"));
mapCustomers.put("2", new Customer("Ali", "Selam"));
mapCustomers.put("3", new Customer("Avi", "Noyan"));

Collection<Customer> colCustomers = mapCustomers.values();
for (Customer customer : colCustomers) {
     // process customer
}
]]></programlisting>
        </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="CSharpClient" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
            >
        <title>CSharp Client <superscript>(Enterprise Edition Only)</superscript></title>
        <para>You can use native C# client to connect to the running Hazelcast instances. All you need is to include
            Hazelcast.Client.dll into your C# project. The API is very similar to Java native client. Note that C# client
            doesn't have automatic reconnection feature. If the node that it connected dies, it will not switch to another member.
            User must connect to another member itself.
            <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[import com.hazelcast.core.HazelcastInstance;

using System;
using System.Collections.Generic;

using Hazelcast.Client;
using Hazelcast.Core;

ClientConfig clientConfig = new ClientConfig();
clientConfig.GroupConfig.Name = "dev";
clientConfig.GroupConfig.Password = "dev-pass";
clientConfig.addAddress("10.90.0.1");

HazelcastClient client = HazelcastClient.newHazelcastClient(clientConfig);
//Allmost all cluster operations that you can do with ordinary HazelcastInstance
//Note that the Customer class must have Serializable attribute or implement Hazelcast.IO.DataSerializable
IMap<String, Customer> mapCustomers = client.getMap("customers");
mapCustomers.put("1", new Customer("Joe", "Smith"));
mapCustomers.put("2", new Customer("Ali", "Selam"));
mapCustomers.put("3", new Customer("Avi", "Noyan"));

ICollection<Customer> colCustomers = mapCustomers.values();
foreach (Customer customer in colCustomers) {
     // process customer
}
]]></programlisting>


        </para>
    </sect2>
</sect1>
