<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!--
  ~ Copyright (c) 2008-2012, Hazel Bilisim Ltd. All Rights Reserved.
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->

<sect1 xml:id="ClientProtocol" version='5.0' xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
       xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
       xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd">
    <title>Client Protocol Specification</title>
    <para>Hazelcast Client Protocol is a TCP protocol that is designed to be simple and yet powerful.
        A client opens a connection to Hazelcast server (default port is 5701) and sends the request command.
        Upon receiving the command, server will execute it and send the response back to the client. Each connection
        needs to send the protocol type first and then authenticate using AUTH command before sending any other command.
        After protocol is set and AUTH is done then the client can use the same connection to send infinite number of
        other commands over the same connection.
    </para>

    <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Request Protocol</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
        General structure of protocol is as follows:
        <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
        COMMAND <arg1>…<argN> #M\r\n
        <s1>…<sM>\r\n
        B1B2…. BM\r\n]]></programlisting>

        Notice that the protocol consists of 3 lines. The first two lines are interpreted as text and there is a new
        line character after each. The first line is called "command line", second is "size line" and the rest is binary
        data.
    </para>

    <para>
        Command line specifies the command and some arguments for that command that can be defined as string.
        These are in general arguments like strings, boolean, integers and longs. The last argument defines the
        number of binary arguments. If there is no argument then it is ok to not provide it or one can simply provide
        #0.
        In case of #0 then next lines can be omitted. That is the client or server will only send the commandline as
        part
        of the protocol
    </para>
    <para>
        Size line defines the size of the binary arguments with space in between.
        This way server is able to parse the binary data.
    </para>

    <para>Here is a sample put command
        <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
        MPUT myMap 0 #2
        5 7
        myKeymyValue]]></programlisting>
    </para>


    <sect2 xml:id="Extension" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
        <title>Entensions</title>

        <para>
            <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Thread id extension</emphasis>
            </para>

            The default protocol doesn't let you to implement a thread safe client implementation. This extension will
            let
            you to pass a thread id together with a flag. Flag will be returned in the response as is and can be used as
            a
            call id. If thread id is passed, only the same thread can unlock the locks. Basically hazelcast will treat
            each
            thread as a different caller on the client side. However with default protocol Hazelcast assumes that there
            is
            only one caller on the client side.

            <para>
        <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
        <thread_id> COMMAND <flag> <arg1>…<argN> #M\r\n
        <s1>…<sM>\r\n
        B1B2…. BM\r\n]]></programlisting>

            </para>
                             å
        </para>

        <para>
            <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Noreply extension</emphasis>
            </para>

            All commands in Hazelcast do return a response from server. However there are several commands where you may
            skip the response by adding "noreply" at the end of the arguments. For those commands server will not return
            a response. Check the command description to see if it supports noreply. Both normal and extended protocols
            support noreply independently.

            <para>
        <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
        MPUT myMap 0 noreply #2
        5 7
        myKeymyValue]]></programlisting>
            </para>
        </para>

    </sect2>


    <sect2 xml:id="CommonArgs" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
        <title>Protocol common arguments</title>


        <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">flag</emphasis>
            Flag is any string value that will be returned by server on answer.
            Server doesn't care about the value that is set here. It will return it back on response
            object.
            This argument can be used as call_id to match the responses to calls.
        </para>

        <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">noreply</emphasis>
            Is an optianal argument and is provied as it is, "noreply". If provided, server will
            not send the response back to client. Commands that retrieve data from server do not have
            <emphasis role="bold">noreply</emphasis>
            as option.
            Must be the last argument before
            <emphasis role="bold">#N</emphasis>
            argument.
        </para>

        <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">name</emphasis>
            Is the name of the data structure. Distributed objects that require name must set this
            argument accordingly.
            Note that almost all commands do require it
        </para>
    </sect2>


    <sect2 xml:id="Response" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
        <title>Response</title>

        <para>
            Responses from server will use the same protocol. The command on response will either be
            <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis>
            or
            <emphasis role="bold">ERROR</emphasis>
            followed by<emphasis role="bold">flag</emphasis>.
        </para>

        <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">A status reply</emphasis>
        </para>

        <para>
            without any value will be

            <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
        OK <flag> \r\n
        ]]></programlisting>

            An error reply will be as follows:

            <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
        ERROR <flag> <error reason> \r\n
        ]]></programlisting>

            Error's will happen only if the request doesn't contain the proper arguments.
        </para>
    </sect2>
</sect1>
